Matthew Rathbone

18 S Bedford Street, #302, Madison WI 53703. 347-450-9876. matthew.rathbone@gmail.com. http://matthewrathbone.com

Overview

I am a seasoned software engineer with experience in offline data processing, and back-end web technologies. I believe that constant measurement, instrumentation, automation, and experimentation are fundamental to building a successful product that can easily evolve to meet the needs of its users.

Professional Experience

Foursquare, New York NY

Nov 2010 - Present

Software Engineer - Data Infrastructure

- Built and supported production batch data processing infrastructure using Hadoop (over 100TB).
- Created ETL pipelines in Map/Reduce to ingest 1TB of daily data, generate other datasets, and feed production systems.
- Worked closely with other engineers to design and produce a suite of software tools to enable easy development and testing of data processing and machine learning algorithms.
- Designed and built several internal web tools to help the whole company to query and visualize largescale datasets.

Drop.io, Brooklyn, NY

May 2010 - Nov 2010

Software Engineer

- Developed a high throughput event-data collection & reporting system to allow real-time and offline reporting.
- Developed a scalable distributed user billing system in order to generate accurate charges for api and disk usage.
- The company was acquired by Facebook in November 2010.

New York University, New York, NY

Jan 2010 - May 2010

Grader - Graduate Operating Systems

• Graded assignments in various languages implementing such as linking, memory paging, resource allocation, and disk-seeking.

Threadneedle Asset Management, London, UK

Aug 2007 - Jun 2009

Software Engineer - Front Office

- Lead engineering on the development of portfolio management software used to manage hundreds of millions of dollars of assets.
- Enhanced legacy software to integrate with strategic in-house platforms and utilize external APIs.
- Worked in a team to create common order processing APIs using an external processing platform. The API's were used across multiple projects.

UBS Investment Bank, London, UK

Oct 2006 - Aug 2007

Business Change Specialist

- Provided structured analysis of internal statistics and processes in co-ordination with global management teams in order to support strategic decision making.
- Played a lead role in the development and deployment of management information systems to meet key business objectives. Delivery was on schedule & within budget.

UBS Securities LLC, New York, NY

Sep 2005 - Sep 2006

Analyst

- Led the data collection and filing of 144a class action lawsuit claims.
- Automated departmental management information reporting, increasing accuracy and validating data.

Education

Courant Institute of New York University, New York, NY

2009 - 2011

MS in Computer Science

- Awarded the 2012 Matthew Smosna Prize for academic achievement.
- Highlighted Courses: Parallel Computing, NLP, Machine Learning
- My machine learning project was featured in New Scientist Magazine

Northumbria University, Newcastle-upon-Type, UK

2001 - 2005

LLB Law Exempting - 2:2

• Thesis: "An international study of corporate manslaughter law".

Activities

Public Speaking

2009 - Present

- Hadoop Summit Conference, San Jose Jun 2013
- Madison Ruby Conference Aug 2012
- Various Meetups Highlights: NYC Machine Learning, Madison Big Data, Mad Railers

Big Data Madison Meetup

Jan 2013 - Present

Organizer

- Meetup group focusing on big data technologies
- arrange speakers, lead the meetup, organize funding, evangelize

NYU Masters Association of Computer Science

Sep 2009 - May 2011

President / Officer

TAM Charity Committee

2008 - 2009

Board Member

• Coordinate with charities, encourage staff participation, arrange funds.